okay Oh 97 yes almost 100 come on three
more please I should invite my mom so
she hacked this morning conversation it
was funny how the heck she managed to
hack assume only God knows
yeah don't join with the two devices
just increase the number yeah 100 101
ok it's like the dogs all right so
let's get back to the auto-encoders
that we have started auto-encoders
generative models right and so let's
restart by having a quick review about
the auto-encoders so again we have an
input at the bottom in pink as now you
can see the colors then you have the
rotation the affine transformation and
then you get the hidden layer again
another rotation and then you get the
final output which we are going to be
trying to enforce to be close to be
similar to the input again you have a
parallel kind of diagram where each
transformation is represented with with
a box right so in this case people call
this network is a two layer neural net
because there are two transformations
but what I actually you know advocated
is that this is a three layer neural net
because for me the layers are the
activations that's kind of what is
usually the definition and then yeah now
uses that new kind of symbols that look
like a box with a round top okay all
right so we have two different diagrams
here because we can switch back and
forth between the representations
sometimes is easier to use the left one
when we want to talk about the single
neurons but then sometimes we prefer to
use the other one which you can also
like you know account for multiple
layers so each like block here or like
the encoder and the decoder can be
several layers as well so again these
two macro modules I guess and so the
input get goes inside an encoder
which gives us a code so h which was
before
hidden representation of a neural net
when we talk about you know auto-encoders
h is called code and therefore we have
an encoder which is encoding the input
into this code and then we have a
decoder which is decoding the code into
whatever representation in this case is
is a similar as the same representation
as the input
okay so on the right hand side you have
an auto-encoder, on the left hand side
you're gonna be seen what is a variational
auto-encoder, alright so there
you go
a variational auto-encoder okay it looks
the same so what's the difference
nothing is missing something so the
first difference is here that instead of
having the hidden layer h now we have
the code is actually made of two things
it's made of one thing that is this kind
of capital E of z and V of z and they're
gonna be representing soon the mean and
the variance of this latent variable
z then we are going to be sampling
from this distribution that has been
parameterize by the encoder and we get
to z, it's my latent variable
my latent representation and then this
latent representation goes inside the
decoder so the parameters that I sample
from like I have a normal distribution
which have some parameters E and V. E and
V are deterministically determined by
the input x but then z is not
deterministic z is a random variable
which which gets sampled from a
distribution which is parameterized by
the encoder okay so let's say h was of
size d now the code here
on the left hand side is going to be of
size two times d right because we had to
represent the all the means and then all
the variances in this case we assume
that we have you know d means and d
variance so each of those components re
are independent okay alright so we can
also think about the classic auto-encoder
as just encoding the means and so if you
encode the mean and you have basically
zero variance you're going to get a
again a deterministic auto-encoder so h
might be in this case d and therefore on
the left-hand side E and V will be total
2d.
since we have d means so does that mean
we're sampling the distributions
it's gonna be one multivariate Gaussian
that is orthogonal and so if you have
all those components that are
independent from each other and
therefore z is going to be a d
dimensional vector but then to sample a
d dimensional vector from a Gaussian you
will need d means and then in this case
the variances because we assuming that
all the other components in the
covariance matrix are all zeros
you have only have the diagonal where
you have all the variances okay so here
just to make a recap you have the
encoder that is mapping this kind of
input distribution into like the input
set of samples into this R 2d and so we
can think in this case that we met from
x to the hidden representation and then
the decoder instead maps the z space
into R n which is back to the original
space of the X and therefore we go from
lower case z into x hat. Someone asked
E of z and the V of z is that the output of
the encoder yeah E of z and V of z are
just parameters that are
deterministically output by the encoder
so the encoder is a deterministic you
know it's just the classical rotation
and squashing and then another fine
transformation so it's just a piece of a
neural network which is outputting some
parameters ok so this is the encoder
which is giving me these parameters E
and V given my input x right so this is
deterministic part then given that we
had these parameters these parameters
are you know giving me a Gaussian
distribution with specific means and
specific variances and from these
variance from this Gaussian distribution
we sample one one sample set okay and
then we decode which means we're gonna
see what means this in a in a second but
basically you're going to be encoding
the
they mean and then you're going to be
adding some additional some noise okay
to that encoding in the in the denoising
auto-encoder we were getting our input
you were adding noise to the input and
then you were trying to reconstruct the
input without noise in here the only
thing that is changed is the fact that
the noise is added to the inner
representation rather rather than to the
input does it make sense yeah that makes
a lot more sense thank you so I noticed
that the notation itself kind of looks
like expected value are we generating
just a normal mean from z or we actually
computing my kind of a weighted average
no no there is no okay so my x instead
of outputting the is outputting let's
say d is gonna be 10 that is the hidden
representation now instead of having 10
values representing the mean we're gonna
have 20 values 10 values are
representing the mean and 10 values are
representing the variances okay so we
just output a vector h here given my x
the first half of the vector represents
the means of a standard deviation of a
Gaussian distribution and the other half
of the vector represents the variances
for the same Gaussian distribution okay
so the component h the first component
h1 is going to be the the mean of the
first Gaussian and then the component
h let's say okay let's call it h2 in
this case is gonna be the variance then
you have h3 it's gonna be another mean
h4 it's gonna be another variance
and so on okay so does that make with
that make z like a 10 dimensional vector
that's sampled from yeah yeah yeah so z
is that here it's gonna be half of these
sides here right so the encoder gives me
twice the dimension of z and then
because you get half of the dimensions
like one set of these are for the memes
and one set of these are the variances
then we sample from a Gaussian that has
these values so the network simply gives
me not just the means as
for the classical auto-encoder but also
gives me some what is the range that I
can pick things from right before when
we were using the classical auto-encoder
here we only have the means and then you
simply decode the means in this case you
not only have the means but also you can
have some variants some variations
across those means okay so auto-encoder
normal auto-encoder is deterministic the
output is deterministic input a function
of the input a variational auto-encoder
the output is not longer a deterministic
it's no longer a deterministic function
of the input is going to be a
distribution given the input right so is
a conditional distribution given the
input so in this case we did see that we
saw similar a similar diagram last time
where we were going from a specific
point on the left hand side to the right
hand side in this case we start here
like a point and then we get through the
encoder you're gonna get some position
here but then there is a addition of
noise right if you only have the mean
you would get just one z but then
given that there is some additional
noise that is due to the fact that we
don't have a zero variance that final
point that final z is not going to be
just one point it's gonna be like a
fuzzy point okay so instead of having
one point now one one X is going to be
mapped into one region of points okay so
is going to be actually taking some
space and then we how do we train the
system, we train the system by
sending this latent variable z back to
the the decoder in order to get these x
a hat and of course it's not going to be
getting it exactly to the original point
because perhaps we haven't yet trained
so we have to reconstruct the original
input and to do that we're going to be
trying to minimize what is the square
distance between the reconstruction and
the original input and then we had the
problem
before like to go to the latent to go
from the latent to the input space we
need to know or to learn the
distribution or to enforce some
distribution last time we were seeing
that we're doing something similar when
we are using the the classical the
standard auto-encoder but we were going
from one point x to one point z and then
back to x right right now instead we are
going to be enforcing a distribution
over these points in the latent space
before we were going through one point
one point at one point and then you
don't know what's happening if you move
around in the latent space remember so
if you have on the left hand side at any
samples you're gonna have automatically
on the other side ten latent variables
but then you don't know how to go
between this input between these you
don't know how to travel in this latent
space because we don't know how this
space behave okay variational auto-encoders
enforce some structure and they
do this by adding a penalty of being
different or far from a normal
distribution so if you have a latent
distribution which is not really
resembling a Gaussian then this term
here will be very strong very high and
when we train a variational auto-encoder
we're going to be training it by
minimizing both this term over here
and this term over here so the term on
the left hand side makes sure that we
can get back to the original position a
term on the right hand side enforce some
structure in the latent space because
otherwise we wouldn't be able to you
know sample from there when we'd like to
use this decoder as a generative model
okay this is maybe not too clear but let
me give you a little bit more things to
think about so how do we actually create
this latent variable z so my z is simply
going to be my mean E of z plus some
you know
some noise epsilon which is a sample
from a normal distribution which is like
a normal multivariate Gaussian
distribution with zero mean an identity
matrix as the covariance matrix which
has each components multiplied by the
standard deviation right so you should be
familiar with this equation here on the
top right this is how you rescale a
random variable epsilon which again is a
normal you have to use this kind of
repair metallization in order to get a
Gaussian that has you know a specific
mean in a specific variant ok, the
noise in the latent variable z just in
coded version of the noise introduced in
the input so there is no noise in the
input you put the input inside the
encoder and then the encoder gives you
two parameters E and variance when you
sample from this distribution you
basically get z and what you get here
it's simply you can write the sampling
part as this one so the problem with
sampling is that we don't know how to
perform back propagation through a
sampling module actually there is no way
to perform back propagation through same
thing because this one is just
generating a new z so how do we get
gradients through this module in order
to train the encoder and so this can be
done if you use this trick which is
called the reparameterization trick
the reparameterization trick allows
you to express your sampling in terms of
you know additions and multiplication
which we can differentiate thrown right
the epsilon is simply a additional input
that is you know coming from whatever
wherever well we don't have any need to
send gradients through this input the
gradients will be coming going through
the multiplication and through the
addition okay
so whenever you have gradients for
training this system the gradient comes
down and then here we can replace the
sampling module with a addition between
E Plus
the epsilon multiplied by the square
root of the variance okay such that now
you have you know addition you know how
to back prop through an addition
therefore you get gradients for the
encoder here a output gradient and then
you can compute the partial derivatives
of the you know final costs with
respect to the parameters in this module
okay so in just in a you know intuition
part this KL here allows me to enforce a
structure in the latent space okay
that's what we think about like that's
how I'd like you to think about this
KL term and so let's actually figure
out how this stuff works okay so we have
two terms in my per ample loss, we have
the first one which is the
reconstruction loss and then there is
the second term which is going to be
these KL this relative entropy term okay
so we have some z in this case which are
spheres bubbles okay in this case why
they are bubbles because if you we add
some additional noise right we had the
means and the means are basically the
center of these points right so you have
one mean here one mean over here one
mean over here one mean over here and then
what the reconstruction term is going to
be doing is the following so if this
means if these bubbles overlap what does
it happen so if you have one mean here and
another mean like one bubble here
another bubble it is overlapping and
there is a region where there is you
know intersection
how can you reconstruct these two points
later on right you can't right you're
following so far if you have a bubble
here and then you have another bubble
here all points on this bubble here will
be reconstructed to the original input
here so you start from an original point
you go to the latent space over here and
then you have some noise you actually
have a volume here then you take another
point and this other point it gets
reconstructed here
right now if these two guys overlap how
can you reconstruct the points over here
so if the points are in this bubble I'd
like to go back to the original point
here if the points are in this bubble
I'd like to go to the other point
but if points are overlapped sorry if
the bubbles are overlapped then you
can't really figure out where to go back
right so then the reconstruction term
we'll just do this the reconstruction
term will try to get all those bubbles
as far as possible such that they don't
overlap because if they overlap then the
reconstruction is not going to be good
and so now we have to fix this so there
are a few ways to fix this right how can
you tell me right now how can we fix
this overlapping issue right why didn't
we have this overlapping issue with the
normal auto-encoder because there is no
variance AHA and so what does it mean
okay can you translate what not being
not having a variance mean the spheres
are not spheres but they're points
correct right so if you have just points
points will never overlap right well
they have to be the exact same point but
you have the exact same point only if
the encoder is dead right or you have
the same input I think well it's
unlikely the two points overlap if now
instead of having points you have
actually volumes well you know volume
can overlap because they are many
infinite points right in that volume
okay so one option is going to be
kill the variance and so you have points and
now this defeats the whole variational
thing right
without this spacey thing by killing the
variance now you don't know anymore
what's happening between the points
right because if you have space like if
they takes volume you can walk around in
the latent space you can always figure
out where to go back if these are points
as soon as you leave this position here
you have no whatsoever whatsoever idea
how
where to go okay anyhow first point we
can kill the variance other option well
the one I show you here I the other
option is gonna get these bubbles as far
as possible right so if they are as far
as possible what's gonna happen in your
Python script so if these these
means right they go very very far then
they will increase a lot a lot a lot
right and then the problem is that
you're going to get infinite right this
stuff is gonna explode because all these
values are try to go as far as possible
such that they don't overlap and then
that's not good okay all right so let's
figure out how the variational variational
auto-encoder fixes this problem. Could you
just clarify what you mean by pushing
the points apart like are you putting
them in a higher dimensional space? No no
no so as they are here so each if you
don't have the variance all those
circles here all those bubbles here are
just points even that we have some
variance they will take some space now
if this space taken by two bubbles
overlaps with another bubble the
reconstruction error will increase
because you have no idea how to go back
to the original point that generated
that sphere and so the network the
encoder has two options in order to
reduce this reconstruction error one
option is going to be to kill the
variance such that you get points the
other option is going to be to send all
those points in any direction such that
they don't overlap okay okay yeah that
makes sense, okay good so a
reconstruction error and gets these
stuff to fly around but then let's
introduce the second term so I would
really recommend you to compute these
relative entropy between the a Gaussian
and a normal distribution such that you
can practice maybe for next week but
then if you compute that relative
entropy you get these stuff right you
get several, four terms basically and
everyone should understand how these
look
no okay I'm just joking I'm gonna be
actually explaining it okay so we have
this expression let's try to analyze a
little bit in more detail what they
these terms represent so the first term
you'd have these variants - log variants
- one so if we graph it it looks like
this you have a linear function right on
the after you know after 2 on the x-axis
and then on the other terms you have
subtracted you subtract a logarithm
which goes to plus infinity like if you
sum a minus logarithm it goes to plus
infinity at zero and then otherwise it's
gonna be just you know decaying so if
you sum the two and subtract one you get
this kind of cute function and if you
minimize this function you get just one
and therefore these shows you how these
term and forces those spheres here to
have a radius of one in each direction
because if it tries to be smaller than
one this stuff you know goes up as crazy
and if the increases here doesn't go as
up as crazy so they are it slightly you
know roughly always at least one
or you know half but it won't be that much
smaller because this stuff you know
increases a lot so in this case we have
enforced the network not to collapse
these bubbles in order to make it grow
them too much right because otherwise
they still get penalized here so then we
have another term here these E of z
everything squared and that's classical
problem which has a minimum over there
and so this term here basically says
that all it means should be condensed
towards zero and so basically you get
like this additional force here by this
purple side and now you get that all
those bubbles get squashed together in
this bigger bubble so here you get the
bubbles of bubbles representation of a
variational auto-encoder
how cute is this very cute
how can you pack more bubbles so what is
the only parameter here which is telling
you the strength of your variational
auto-encoder
it's gonna be simply the dimension d
because you know given a dimension you
always know how many bubbles you can
pack in a larger bubble right so it's
just a function of the dimension you
pick and you choose for your hidden
layer, though is the reconstruction last
the first term the yellow term is that
the one that actually pushes the bubbles
further apart and not gonna the rest of
it is what kind of keeps them from doing
that right so the reconstruction would
push things around because we have these
additional taking volumes thing right so
if we wouldn't be taking volumes the
reconstruction term wouldn't be pushing
anything away because it don't overlap
given that we actually have some
variance the variance will have these
points actually taking some volume and
therefore this reconstruction will try
to get those points away so if you check
again those few animations I'll show you
so we had at the beginning those were
the points with additional noise now you
get the reconstruction that is you know
pushing everything away then you get the
variance it is assuring you that those
little bubbles don't collapse and then
you had the final term which is the
spring term because it's the quadratic
term in the loss which is basically
adding these additional pressure such
that all the little guys get you know
packed towards zero but they don't overlap
because there is the reconstruction term
so no overlap due to the reconstruction
size not going to smaller than one
because of the first part of the
relative entropy and then all these guys
are parked again for the quadratic part
which is the spring force
it's a term something that needs to be
tuned like hyper parameter kind of thing
so the beta is the actual in the
original version of this variation
auto-encoder there was no beta and then there
is a paper which is the beta variation
of auto-encoder just to say that you can
use a hyper parameter to change how much
these two terms you know contribute for
the final loss. This loss the second
loss term with the beta that's the KL
divergence? yeah then the normal
distribution rate yeah between the
z which is coming from a Gaussian
of mean E and variance V and then the
second term is going to be this normal
distribution and so this term tries to
get z to be as close as possible to a
normal distribution in the space V
dimensional space okay and this formula
that you that's a generic this is so I
would recommend you to take a paper and
pen and then then try to write the
relative entropy between a Gaussian and
a normal distribution and you should get
all these terms the relative entropy so
yeah this lKL is the relative entropy
yeah so just look up the formula for the
relative entropy which is telling you
basically how far to distributions are
and the first distribution is going to
be a multivariate Gaussian and the
second one is going to be a normal
distribution right yeah normal
distribution is not the same thing the
Gaussian has a mean vector and the
covariance matrix the normal has 0 mean
and identity matrix for the covariance
matrix we said earlier though that the z
should not have covariance it should be
diagonal right yeah yeah so all it's
gonna be diagonal but the values on the
diagonal
those V variances okay it's an off-center
big normal versus a centered in normal
small normal so it's off center and then
each direction is scaled by the by the
standard deviation right of that
dimension so if you have a large
standard deviation in one dimension it
means that in that direction is very
very spread, make sense? but that there is
both a line it's a line on the d axis
right because again all the components
are independent yeah is the
reconstruction loss the pixel wise
distance between the final out and the
original image? The reconstruction loss
we we saw that last week and we have two
options for the reconstruction was one
was the binary for binary data and we
have the binary cross-entropy and the
other one is going to be instead the
real value of one so such that you can
use the half or one DMS MSC right so
these are the reconstruction losses we
can use for example you talk more with
me than with Yann good now well not
good you should talk as well with Yann
but we should be going over the the
notebook such that we can see how to
code the stuff and also play with the
distributions because before again the
main point was that before we were
mapping points to points and back to
points right right now instead you're
gonna map points to space and then space
to points but then also all the space
now is going to be all cover by these
bubbles because of several factors right
if you have some space between these
bubbles then you have no idea how to go
from this region here back to the input
space right instead of variation
auto-encoder gets you to this very
well-behaved coverage you know these
nice covers of the latent space okay
good I can't see you you miss you guys
okay so good, are there any questions so far? I
hope you can see stuff I just give
feedback, can you see stuff? yeah yes yep so
work get pDL conda activate pDL and
Jupyter notebook boom okay so I'm gonna
be covering now the VAE and so now I'm gonna
just execute everything such that this
stuffs are training and then I'm gonna
be explaining things alright so at the
beginning I'm gonna be just import
all random [ __ ] as usual then I have a
display routine we don't care don't add
it to the notes I have some default
values for the random seed such that
you're gonna get the same numbers I get
then here I just use the MNIST dataset
we modify MNIST from Yann device
I set the CPU or GPU in theory I could
have used GP one because my Mac here
actually has a GPU and then I have my
variational auto-encoder okay so my
variational auto-encoder has two parts as a
encoder here let me turn on the line
numbers so my encoder goes from 784
which is the sides size of the input to
this square for example d in this case
is 20 so 400 and then from d square I go
to 2 times d which is gonna be half of
my means and half is gonna be for my
Sigma squares for my variances the other
case the other the decoder instead picks
only d right you can see right d here we
go from d to d square and then from d
square to 794 such that we match the
input dimensionality and then finally I
have a sigmoid
why do we have a sigmoid? because my input
is going to be limited from zero to one
there are images from zero to one then
there is a module here which is called
reparameterise and if we are
training we use the reparameterisation
part, could you just say again
why you use the sigmoid in the? yeah
because my data it's leaving between
zero and one so I have those digits from
the MNIST and they are they are
values like the values of the digits are
going to be from 0 to 1 so I'd like to
have my network this module here outputs
things that goes from minus infinity to
plus infinity if I send it through a
sigmoid this stuff sends things through
like 0 to 1 okay when you say the values
of the digits you mean the deactivations
right?
so I use the MNIST dataset and this
is going to be both my input and also my
targets right and the images and the
values of these images will be ranging
between 0 to 1 like is a real value each
pixel can be between 0 and 1 yeah I
think actually the the inputs are binary
so the inputs are all 0 or 1 but my
network will be outputting a real range
between 0 & 1
so reparameterization we have the we
what do we do here so reparameterization
given a mu and a log variance
explain later why we use log variance if
you are in a you know in training we
compute the standard deviation is going
to be log variance multiplied by 1/2 and
then I take the exponential and so I get
the standard deviation from the log
variance and then I get my epsilon which
is simply sampled from a normal
distribution which with whatever size I
have here right so standard deviation I
get the size I create a new tensor and I
fill it with a normal distribution data
then I return the epsilon multiply by
the standard deviation and I add the mu which
is what I show you before if I am NOT
training I don't have to add noise right
so I can simply return my mu so I use
this network in a deterministic way the
forward mode is the following
so here we have that the encoder get the
input which is going to be reshaped into
you know these things such that
basically I enroll the images into a
vector then the encoder is going to be a
output output in something and I will
shape that one such that I have batch
size two and then d where d is the
dimension of the mean and the dimension
of the variances then I have mu which is
the mean simply the first part right of
these guys of this d and then the log
variance is going to be the other guy
and then I have my z which is going to
be my latent variable it's going to be
these reparameterisation given my mu
and the logvar why do I use a logvar
you tell me why do I use a logvar
right right right so given that
variances are only positive if I compute
the log allows you to output the full
real range for the encoder right so you
can use the whole real range and then I
define my model as this VAE and I send it
to the device here I define the
optimization optimizer
and then I define my loss function which
is the sum of two parts the binary cross
entropy between the input and the
reconstruction which is here so I have
the x_hat and then the X and then I
try I sum all of them and then the KL
divergence so we have the var which is
the you know linear then you have the
minus logvar which is the logarithmic
flip down and then minus one and then we
have the mu and then we try to minimize
this stuff right
all right so training scripts it's very
simple right
so you have the model which is
outputting the prediction x_hat let me
let's see here right forward outputs the
output of the decoder the mu and the log
var so here you get the model
you feed the input you get x_hat mu
logvar you can compute the loss using the
x_hat, x, mu and logvar, x being the input
but also the target and then we you know
yeah we add the item for the loss we
clean up the gradient from the previous
steps perform computational compute the
partial derivatives and then you step
and then here I just do the testing and
do some caching for later on so we
started with initial error of 500
roughly 514 this is pre before training
and any goes immediately immediately
down to 200 and then goes down to 100
okay and so now I'm gonna be showing you
a few of the results this is the input I
feed to the network and the untrained
network reconstructions of course look
like [ __ ] right but okay that's fine so
we can keep going and there's gonna be
the first epoch right cool
second epoch third fourth and so on
right and it looked better and better
of course so what can we do right now a
few things we can do for example now we
can simply sample z from normal
distribution and then I decode this
random stuff right so this doesn't come
from our encoder and I show you now what
the decoder does whenever you sample
from the distribution that the latent
variable should have been following and
so these are a few examples of how
sampling from the latent distribution
you know gets decoded into something we
got a nine here we go to zero we got
some five so some of the regions are
very well defined nine two but then other
regions like this thing here
or this thing here or the number 14 here
they don't really look like well like
digits this is because why what's the
problem here we haven't really covered
the whole space I just trained for one
minute
if I trained for 10 minutes it's going
to be just working perfectly okay so
here those bubbles don't yet fill the
whole space right and it's the same
problem which you would have with a
normal out encoder without this
variational thing right with very normal
auto-encoders you don't have you know any
kind of structure any kind of defined
behavior in the regions between
different points with the variational
auto-encoder we actually take the
space and enforce that the
reconstruction of the all these region
actually are to make sense again so
let's do some cute stuff and then I am
done here I just show you a few digits
and so let's pick two of them for
example let's pick three and eight which
is going to be let me show you here so
we'd like to find a interpolation now
between a five and a four okay and this
is my five reconstructed and our four
reconstructed so if I perform a linear
interpolation in the latent space and I
then send it to the decoder we get this
one so the five gets morphed into a four
you can see slowly but it looks like
crap let's try to get something that
stays on a manifold so let's get for
example these three so it's going to be
number one number one and then let's say
maybe these 14 here
so I do interpolation of these guys here
you can see my auto-encoder actually
fixed those kind of issues here and then
you can see now how the three gets those
little edges closed to look like an
eight right and so all of them look like
kind of legit no it's just kind of a
three kind of a three a three day became
an eight right and so you can see how
now by walking in the latent space we
get to reconstruct things that look
legit in the input space right this
would have never worked with a normal
auto-encoder finally I'm gonna show you a
few nice representation of the
embeddings of the means for this train
auo-encoder so here I'll just show you a
collection of the embeddings of you know
the test data set and then I perform a
like a dimensionality reduction and then
I show you how the encoder clusters all
the means in different regions in the
latent space and so here is what you
get when you train this variational
auto-encoder so this is the the beginning
when the network is not trained
you can still see you know clusters of
digits but then as you keep training
well at least you know after five epochs
you get these groups to be you know
separated and then I think if you keep
training more you should have like more
separation okay so here I'm basically
doing the testing part I get all the
means so my model outputs x_hat, mu and
logvar right and so my means I append
them I append all my mus into this mean
list I append all the logvars in this
logvars list and I append all the y's
to these labels list during the testing
part right so this is testing and so I
have like a list here of codes which is
a I have the mu, logvar and then y's
right so here later on I
put those lists inside my a dictionary
and then later here below I compute a
dimensionality reduction for epoch zero
epoch five and epoch ten so I use this
TSNE which is a technique for reducing
the dimensions of the codes which are
twenty right now the dimension height is
20 so I fit I get my X is gonna be let's
say the first thousand component first
thousand samples of the means and then I
get these Es which are basically a 2d
projection somehow of these twenty
dimensional mus okay and then I show
you in this chart here how these 2d
projections they look at epoch 0 before
training the network because this one is
before the first training epoch and then
at epoch five you can see how the
network gets all this mess here to be
you know kind of more nicely put here I
didn't visualize the variances I'm
thinking whether I can if I'm able to do
that as well not sure so each of these
points represent the location of the
mean after training the variational
auto-encoder
I haven't represented the area that
these means are actually taking okay are
that means supposed to be random at epoch 0
the randomness is in the encoder right
but then you still feed to the encoder
and those inputs digits so the input
digits all the ones are kind of similar
right so if you perform a random
transformation of those similarly
looking initial vectors
you're going to have similarly looking
transformed versions but then they are
not necessarily grouped all together
like most of them are for it for example
let's say these are 1s let me turn on
the color bar so we can see what this
stuff is
so let's say these are the zeros these
over here so all zeros look like they
all look similar therefore even a random
projection of those zeros will all be
kind of together what you can see
instead is gonna be this purple is all
spread around right so means the force
there yeah there are very many ways of
drawing four you know someone right is
closest the top someone doesn't so if
you see on the right hand side inside
all the fours are almost all here right
there is just a little cluster here next
to the nine because you can you can
think about if you if you write a four
like that it's very similar to write a
nine right and so you had these fours
here that are very close to the nines
just because of how people drew this
specific fours okay nevertheless they
are still clustered over here you get
all these things are spread around and
so this is very bad
nevertheless they tell you this that
this diagram here shows you that there
is very little variance across the
drawing of a zero okay so it shows you
like somehow there is a specific mode it
is very concentrated here but it's
really not concentrated for these guys
so I'm just curious like what are some
other some other like like motivations
or usages of variational auto-encoder
like so the main point was the whenever
I show you in class the two weeks ago a
generative model you cannot have a
generative model with a classical
auto-encoder in this case here again I train
I didn't train this stuff a lot if you
train it longer you can have better
performance here and the point is that
my input z comes from just this
random distribution okay and then by
sending this random number here a random
a number coming from a normal
distribution you send an inside this
decoder
if this
this is a coder is actually a powerful
decoder then this stuff will actually
draw very nice shapes or numbers like
for example those two images I show you
of the two faces in the first part of
the class last time those are simply you
take a number from my random
distribution you feed it to a decoder
and the decoder is going to be drawing
you this very beautiful picture of
whatever you trained this decoder on okay
and you cannot use a standard
auto-encoder to get these kinds of properties
because again here we enforce the
decoder to reconstruct meaningful or
good-looking reconstruction when they
are sample from this normal distribution
therefore later on we can sample from
this normal distribution feed things to
the decoder and the decoder will
generate stuff that looks like legit
right if you didn't train the decoder in
order to perform a good reconstruction
when you sample from this normal
distribution you wouldn't be able to
actually get anything meaningful okay
that's the big takeaway here next time
we're going to be seen said
generative adversarial network
and how they how they are very similar
to these stuff we have seen today on hi
Alfredo I have a question for the
yellow bubble yellow yeah
each yellow bubble comes from one input
example yeah so if we have 1000 I don't
know what images or 1000 inputs
that means we have 1000 exactly yellow
bubbles yeah and each yellow bubble
it comes from the the E of z, V of z
distribution together with the noise
added to latent variable so the bubble
come from here let me show you should I
show you this one is okay or should I
say okay so here you get these X and
these X goes inside the model right
whenever you send these X through the
model it goes inside forward so X goes
inside here and then it goes inside the
encoder right okay and then from the
gives me this mu logvar from which I
just extract the mu and logvar okay so
so far is everything it's like a normal
auto-encoder okay
the bubble comes here so my z now comes
out from these self-reparameterise and
this self-reparameterise is gonna be
working in a different way if we are in
the training loop or we are not in the
training loop so if we are not in the
training loop I just returned the min so
there is no bubble when I use the
testing part ok so I get the best
value the encoder can give me if I am
training instead what this is what
happens so my I compute the standard
deviation from this logvar so I get the
logvar I divid it by two and then I take
the exponential right so I have E to the
one half logvar such that you get you
know the standard deviation and then the
epsilon it can be simply an a d
dimensional vector sample from a normal
distribution and so this one is one
sample coming from this normal
distribution and the normal distribution
it's you know like a sphere in d
dimensions right a sphere with the
radius which is going to be square root
of d but then so here at the end
you simply resize that thing the point
is that every time you go you called is
reparameterization the reparameterize
function you can I get a different
epsilon because epsilon it's sampled
from a normal distribution right so
given a mu and given a logvar you're
gonna be getting every time different
Epsilon's and therefore these stuff here
if you call it a hundred times it's
gonna give you 100 different points all
of them cluster in mu with the radius of
you know roughly standard deviation and
so this is the line which returns you
every time just one sample but if you
call this in a for loop you're gonna get
you know a cloud of points all
them centered mu which has a specific
radius okay and so this is where we get
these bubbles come from the sampling and
of these thing right I have to run it
100 times if you want 100 samples you
get 100 times you had to run into 100
times this reparameterization gives
you every time a different point which
is you know parameterize by this
location and this kind of you know up
you know volume yeah and this comes from
the mu and log variance comes
from one sample one input example yeah
yeah yeah so my one input x here gives
me one mu and gives me one logvar and
this one mu and well one logvar gives
me z which is one sample from the whole
distribution if you run this function
here 1,000 times you're gonna get 1,000
z which all of them will take this
volume right off okay got it got it
thank you
of course I have a question about auto-encoders,
sorry, encoders and decoders in general
yeah it looks like in this
implementation
it's like fairly straightforward in
terms of like it just has like a couple
linear layers with a relu and a
sigmoid are most like I like I
previously they seemed encoders where
there's like attention all this
stuff like is is this is something kind
of as basic as this it seems like it's
pretty satisfactory like is that I mean
are are they usually this basic or
more complex okay okay that does I think
softball for me so everything we see in
class is things that I've tried it works
and it's fairly a representative of what
is sufficient to get this stuff to run
so you know I'm running on my laptop on
the MNIST data set you can run several of
this kind of test and play and so today
we have seen how you can encode how can
you code up a
auto-encoder, all you need is like three
lines four lines of code which are like
like what are the differences between
the playing an auto-encoder and so the
difference is that you have the
reparameterization
reparameterization, reparameterize module
method here and then you know just these
three lines over here right so you have
like six lines plus the relative entropy
the architecture that's completely
different so it's completely orthogonal
right one thing is gonna be at the
architecture which is based on the
current input you can use a
convolutional net you can use a
recurrent net you can use anything you
want and the other thing is the fact
that you convert some deterministic
Network into a network that allows you
to sample and then generate samples from
a distribution okay so we never had to
talk about distributions before we
didn't know how to generate
distributions now with generative model
you can actually generate data which are
basically a you know you say like a
bending a rotation or a transformation
of whatever with the original Gaussian
right so we had this multivariate
gaussian and then the decoder takes this
ball and then it shapes it to make it
look like the input the input maybe like
something curved you have this bubble
here this big bubble of bubbles and then
you the decoder gets it back to whatever
looks like how the input looks like so
all you need depends on the specific
data you are using for MNIST this is
sufficient if you're using a
convolutional version is maybe worth
working much better the point is that
this class was about variational auto-encoder
know how to get crazy stuff all the
crazy stuff is simply you know adding
several of these things I've been
teaching you so far but the bit about
variational auto-encoder I think it was
covered mostly here okay okay thanks
other questions? no okay okay that was it
okay thank you so much for joining us
okay everyone almost left 70% see you
next week bye all right okay